**Julianne Van Wagenen**<a href="mailto:jvanwagenen.github.io">jvanwagenen.github.io</a> | Cambridge, MA, USA | +1 517 505 5057 | jvanwagenen@hbs.com

## **SUMMARY**

Graduate-level program and content manager; ex-university instructor; researcher; webmaster; project manager and book/journal managing editor; detail-oriented self-starter who enjoys and excels at problem solving in a team environment; 15+ years experience in web design and ed program creation/coordination

## **SKILLS**

Interpersonal Communication Team building & Collaboration Academic Research and Writing Attention to Detail

Project Management Strategic & Organizational Planning Meaningful Goal-driven Content Creation Problem Solving

Qualitative & Quantitative Research Presentations & Public Speaking Adobe Suite, HTML, CSS Foreign Languages

## **RELEVANT EXPERIENCE**

# HBS Online, Harvard Business Analytics Program (HBAP)

Online Learning Manager

Boston, MA July 2022 – Present

- Manage courses and seminars on an online course platform: includes liaising with faculty and TFs, updating course content, coordinating online live sessions, office hours, and simulations across the term, managing the courses in Slack
- Create videos using Photoshop and Premiere as needed: includes videos for social media posts, new faculty videos for the online orientation course, a peer-learning orientation video series for new students
- Create and manage much of the supplemental programming HBAP offers: including Startup Academy, an 8week online course (2023; created with a team and executed); HBAP Pitch Competition, a term-long program with a mentor series, pitch workshops, submission round, live online finals, and LinkedIn Live event for the winner (2023-24; updated and executed); HBAP Summer Programming, a 2-month set of programming for all 1000+ current and past HBAP participants (2023-24; created and executed); Career Services webinar series (2024; updated and executed); D^3 Cubie Awards and Ceremony (2024; worked with a team to create and execute on a short timeline)
- Act as the accessibility lead for the program: includes remediating videos and slide decks, creating audio descriptions and elaborated transcripts, and working with program partners to implement all updates on in the
- Work with a team, term over term, to plan and execute HBAP's in-person 3-day immersions on HBS Campus

Harvard University Cambridge, MA January 2022 – July 2022

Postdoctoral Fellow

- Book project proposal selected from a wide group of candidates from around the world
- Work on research and publishing related to countercultural song, modern mythologies, mass tourism, and travel ethics; have published and peer-reviewed book and articles (see below).

# Pirandello in Translation - Stories for a Year

Web Developer, Translator (pirandellointranslation.org)

2021 - Present

- Designed and built the book-project website, which hosts a growing number of original Pirandello translations
- Worked with a team to create project goals, wire-frame design, take feedback, and build consensus to finalize
- Continue to work with a team to coordinate translation and presentation of digital publication of translations

# Pirandello Society of America

**Board of Directors** 

2019 - Present

- Help organize the scheduling and program-details for our quarterly board-member meetings
- Present and lead discussions: such as moving general membership payment online; website renovation; website design; updating membership policies and costs; hosting our journal archive online; organizing annual events
- Work with content editors to clearly communicate complex issues and reach board consensus
- Work with content editors to elaborate and enact all society projects from inception to delivery (new membership payment system; digital archive; annual journal production; printing costs and options; etc.)

# Pirandello Society of America

Web Developer (pirandellosociety.org)

2019 - 2023

- Designed and built the literary-society and academic-journal website
- Worked with a team to create project goals, wire-frame design, take feedback, and build consensus to finalize

# The Pirandello Society Annual Journal

2017 - 2023Managing Editor

- Design and build each the annual journal using InDesign; create cover designs in Gimp
- Copy-edit the content and formatting for the entire journal
- Work with the content editors to come to a consensus on cover design and other formatting questions
- Prepare journal for printer; communicate with printer across the entire process to assure print accuracy

Tsinghua University

Beijing, China

Instructor, Thesis Advisor Fall 2018 - Fall 2021

- Created and taught courses in the Institute of World Literatures and Cultures: "Journey to Italy: Travel Writing since the Grand Tour", "Rereading the Divine Comedy with Borges", "Postcolonial Literature in the 1900s"
- Instituted an initiative in sophomore seminars that helped students to excel in academic writing
- Helped organize the curriculum of IWLC in terms of pedagogical and content goals and program continuity
- Organized a Graduate School Application workshop; organized workshops, mentored students one-on-one
- Advised senior-theses; organized time, set deliverable dates; advised on research, citational styles, clarity

# University of Southern California Lecturer

Los Angeles, CA Spring 2018

Taught 3 courses in Italian language, worked with a team to create and grade bi-weekly assessments

Worked with a team to create a community-based component to courses; facilitated weekly language table

# Milan and Siena: Harvard Summer School Study Abroad

Milan and Siena, Italy

Coordinator, Instructor

Summer 2016, Summer 2017

- Worked on a team to develop and teach the language-program courses for a new study-abroad program
- Worked with a team to organize the housing, field trips, events, reservations for a group of 30 undergraduates
- Led 2 sections of 8-credit Aesthetics & Ethics course taught during the summer abroad
- Handled all translation, documentation, and emergency issues for study-abroad students

**Monad Media** Cambridge, MA

Owner, Project Manager

2014 - 2017

- Founded company that provided economical web development to academic projects
- Worked with creative teams in Harvard GSAS and Libraries to create wire frames and manage web development
- Led project management, including timelines, deadlines, cost analysis, bug fixes, etc., for all projects

# metaLAB (at) Harvard

Cambridge, MA

Project Manager, Principal Investigator

2013 - 2017

- Participated as a creative lead in metaLAB principal meetings; wrote grant applications for various projects
- Worked with a team of professors to create interdisciplinary courses (offered FAS and GSD); created syllabi, created and taught innovate discussion-sections/studios; organized summer developer workshops and new digital-humanities projects
- Project manager for <u>curarium.com</u>; managed developer team using Redmine, worked with advisors at the Berkman Klein Center, tracked deadlines and bug fixes, presented platform at conferences and workshops

**Harvard University** Cambridge, MA

Course Developer, Instructor, Thesis Advisor

2013 - 2017

- Developed and taught courses in in the Romance Languages and Literatures department
- Wrote grant applications; won 2017 Elson Family Arts Initiative Fund to Support Arts in Curricula
- Won the Harvard University Department of Romance Languages and Literatures Teaching Prize in 2016
- Won the Derek Bok Center for Teaching and Learning Certificate of Excellence for every semester I was eligible
- Organized Chiasmi Graduate Student Conference in 2013
- Presented at panels or invited talks and/or organized and chaired panels at over 20 conferences and events

**Dudley House Library** Cambridge, MA Head Librarian 2012 - 2017

Hired and managed a team of between 5 and 8 librarians; managed library with team

Harvard University Cambridge, MA Doctoral Researcher 2011 - 2017

- Completed my doctoral work on time and with a successful dissertation that was published in 2023
- 2013-14 Video Coordinator for Colloquium series; coordinated and managed production of video interviews
- Copy-edited various projects, for example, Johanna Drucker's Graphesis (2014)
- Worked as a translator for the Italian *cantautori* in Translation website <u>theitaliansong.com</u>

# The American in Italia Magazine

Columnist

Rome, Italy 2009 – 2014

- Met monthly deadlines, worked with editor to revise, copy edit; published over 40 articles (see below for link)

# Physical Chemistry Department, Michigan State University

East Lansing, MI 2009 – 2011

Web Developer, Data Analyst

- Created a website (Dreamweaver) for the PI's research project on the dipole moment of white-dwarf stars
- Wrote programs in Terminal that ran on the university super computer and simulated how molecules would act when put under the intense atmospheric pressure of a white-dwarf star; collected/organized all post-run data

# PUBLICATIONS (JVANWAGENEN.GITHUB.IO/WRITING)

## **Public-Audience Articles**

"The Wonderland" Column (2008-2014), 43 articles, in The American in Italia

Review. <u>Mistero Buffo.</u> By Dario Fo, performed by The Poets' Theatre. La Voce di New York, 2016. 7 Apr. 2016. Review. <u>Digital Humanities.</u> By Anne Burdick, Johanna Drucker, Peter Lunenfeld, Todd Presner, Jeffrey Schnapp. Romance Sphere. Web. 5 May 2013.

Review. <u>Italia reloaded. Ripartire con la cultura</u>. Christian Caliandro and Pier Luigi Sacco. *Romance Sphere.* Web. 7 May 2012.

Review. <u>The Electric Information Age Book: McLuhan/Agel/Fiore and the Experimental Paperback</u>. By Jeffrey Schnapp and Adam Michaels. *Romance Sphere*. Web. 15 Apr. 2012.

## **Academic Books**

Mythologist in Microgroove: A Study of Italian Myths and Cultural Shifts with Fabrizio De André on Lead Vocals. Fairleigh Dickinson University Press (2023).

# **Academic Book Chapters**

"Le piazze d'Italia: de Chirico's Prophetic Vision of Public Space in Destination Italy" in Interpreting Urban Spaces in Italian Cultures, edited by Andrea Scapolo and Angela Porcarelli, 139-156. Amsterdam: Amsterdam University Press, 2023.

## **Academic Articles**

"Corto Maltese, Counterculture Hero: A Unifying Figure for Francesco Guccini and Fabrizio De André's Revolutionary Visions." Italica. 99.2 (Summer 2022): pp. 199-221.

"The Double Life of Fiddler Jones: Between Edgar Lee Masters and Fabrizio De André" Gradiva: International Journal of Poetry 58 (Fall 2020): pp. 146-162. Stony Brook University.

"It's All Relative: Modernism and Science." Pirandello Society Annual 32 (Spring 2020): pp. 13-21.

"Masters vs. Lee Masters: The Legacy of the Spoon River Author between Illinois and Italy." Forum Italicum 53 (3) (Fall 2019): pp. 679-698. Stony Brook University.

"Chess Set Theory: The Fractal Realism of Bontempelli and Borges." South Central Review 36 (1) (Spring 2019): 104-128. Johns Hopkins University Press.

"Canto X of Gerusalemme liberata." Harvard Tasso Lab. Romance Sphere: 2-11. Web. May 2013.

# **EDUCATION**

Harvard University - Graduate School of Arts and Sciences

Cambridge, MA

PhD, Italian Studies

September 2011 - May 2017

DePaul University - Honors College

Chicago, IL

BA, with High Honors, Double Major in Italian Studies and English Literature

September 2002 - March 2006

## **LANGUAGES**

English (native), Italian (near-native), Spanish (intermediate), French (basic)

## **SOFTWARE**

Adobe Creative Suite (Premiere, Express, Dreamweaver, InDesign, Photoshop (Gimp)); Canvas; Redmine; Excel; Atom (HTML and CSS); GitHub

## **MEDIA COVERAGE**

Research Featured in Volpe, Andrea. "Being Human Now: How Innovative Methods and Contemporary Concerns are Helping Humanities Scholars Re-Envision the Past and Imagine the Future." Colloquy. Spring 2016. 12-17.